[Music]
hello everybody good to see you all
wishing everybody a very happy
independence day let me see who all is
there pratik roy vinayak
kolcheri aryan sudha amit
good evening good evening good evening
everybody
good evening mahesh patil ajay nyogi
nihal
good evening good day to everybody great
to see you all
so today is the 37th live
episode of azkabajit today we discussed
indian history and before i begin i
would like to tell you if you are not
aware yet that the
taliban is in the process of entering
kabul right now
they have already entered kabul and the
president of afghanistan or ex-president
mr
ashraf ghani is on a plane
he has left the country
so things are moving fast the u.s
occupation or involvement in afghanistan
has come to an end
and the taliban occupation has just
begun
so that's what's happening right now
yesterday we discussed this with abhijit
ayamitra
i i
realized that the sound on his side was
a little bit low i apologize for that
it's a learning process i've not done
this live before with a guest so
next time it will be better i can assure
you of that
okay so today is indian history like we
know and let's
begin with today's questions
let's begin with the first question
so this is by saeeda who says can you
tell us the truth about the 1946
naval mutiny
that's an interesting question thus far
i've been taking questions about ancient
more ancient indian history this is more
recent indian history but it's a very
important
chapter in the
pre-independent sister of india
it it's something that actually
triggered off
the
independence of india it hastened
india's independence so here's what
happened
uh
the uk along with its allies went to war
in 1938 39 39 i think it is yes the
second world war
and a significant number of the british
troops were actually indian troops more
than two and a half million
indian troops
fought in the second world war on behalf
of the british that's 25 lakhs more than
25 lakhs it's an enormous number
so this war went on for several years it
ended in 1945 with the defeat of the
japanese the germans were defeated in
europe and after a few months later the
japanese
were defeated
in 1945 with the twin atomic bombings of
hiroshima and nagasaki so that brought
the second world war to an end
and this war basically crippled the
united kingdom
economically
so it became very difficult for that
country to hold on to its overseas
possessions
including india especially when india
had been already sucked dry of all its
wealth it was there was nothing left for
india to give to the uk
all of the indian wealth had already
already been taken over
so the british basically began slowly
disbanding the indian indian armed
forces
right
there was a process of demobilization
which means that
soldiers
and sailors etc were released from
service
now this process took a very long time
it was a slow bureaucratic process now
the we had this big
quite significant sizeable indian navy
the royal indian navy rin
which had ports which was based in
several ports karachi mumbai
vishakhapatnam madras
kolkata
in the andamans as well even in
in the middle east even in singapore
and
places like indonesia etc so it was a
very
well spread out
naval force now what happened was that
this process of demobilization was going
on and all these great all these sailors
who had fought for the british in
various parts of the world they were
basically uh put on shore leave and they
were basically
just kept idle
and they were basically waiting they
were essentially waiting to be
demobilized so this process went on for
a long time the treatment was very bad
the salaries were the wages were very
low the food was terrible there was a
great deal of racism and whatnot and
also at this time what was happening was
that the
indian national army
uh had captured the nation's uh
imagination because of the
way in which it fought the british in
the in the eastern theater the battle of
kohima the battle of imphal the burmese
campaign
uh the international national army ina
sawash chandra bose's army did indeed
lose
at the end
but it captured the public's imagination
the
nation's imagination that yes indians
can actually fight the british and make
them bleed
right now many of these indian ina
soldiers were captured and they were put
on trial etc so there was a great deal
of discontent so this is the background
to the 1946 naval revolt so what
happened was that in i think february
uh in bombay now mumbai
in mumbai this revolt was triggered off
a number of uh sailors went on strike
they began to refuse uh
uh accepting or obeying orders from
their european their british uh officers
etc they started saluting with the left
left hand they started painting graffiti
on the walls quit india and things like
that
and because of the ill treatment they
were receiving from the british
superiors there was a great deal of
racism
they were called sons of and
sons of coolies and jungles
and even worse things black bastards and
whatnot
these are some of the things that the
food was terrible the treatment was
overall terrible
so these guys revolted
initially it was just a small number 200
300 of them who revolted but very
quickly what happened is that this
spread like a it went viral the correct
terminology it went viral because these
guys captured the communications
infrastructure of the of the royal
indian navy the wireless systems and all
and within a couple of days this revolt
had spread all over the indian navy
royal indian navy karachi went on strike
uh vishakhapatnam madras went on strike
the the even in the andamans the royal
indian navy ships went uh basically
revolted they stopped obeying orders and
all that
and within a few days
more than 70 almost 78 ships had
revolted naval ships warships had
revolted against the british four
british occupiers of india
and more than 20 000 uh sailors were
involved in this and not just the
sailors it was the population the
civilian population of mumbai of karachi
that revolted against the british the
whole entire city of mumbai the entire
city of karachi went on strike there
were protests there were demonstrations
trains were burned property was damaged
europeans were heckled and pushed and
all that it was becoming really
dangerous for the europeans
and all the indian sailors had
had control of these naval ships with
their powerful guns and weaponry
so this became a very dangerous
situation it within a few days if they
had this had not been stopped if this
had not been contained the indian
army
would have also revolted 25 lakh
soldiers
imagine what would have happened if the
indian army had joined this reward if
they had come to know about this
the navy the naval guys had the control
of the wireless infrastructure and also
they were able to communicate with
various ships and very in far-off
locations in india
but this was not connected to the army
network
that's why the army did not come to know
about this if they had known this would
have been a nationwide uprising on a
scale greater than the 1857 war and the
british would have been wiped out in a
bloody manner in 28 to 48 hours
there was no way they could have
survived this sort of a revolution
now what happened was that these are
these sailors they took possession of
the ships and all the infrastructure
they placed three flags on each ship
the congress flag the muslim league flag
and the communist flag these were the
three main parties political parties in
india
so three flags the congress flag the
muslim league flag and the communist
flag and this spread all across india
even in karachi
in various places so this and it had a
great deal of popular support so what
the british did was that they ordered
the police
to quell the the rioting and all that in
the cities of mumbai and karachi the
police refused to cooperate
the police kind of joined the people
in uh
protesting against the british this went
beyond non-cooperation this was becoming
a violent insurrection
then they had to bring in the indian
army
the british indian army and then there
was a bloody massacre in the city of
mumbai more than 200 people official
figures say that more than 200 civilians
were killed and many thousands were
injured i would say that the unofficial
real figures would be many thousands
must have been killed in this
discriminate firing
on unarmed civilian protesters and the
same sort of thing happened in karachi
also it must have happened in other
places too but we're not sure i mean we
don't have the records because these
records were all british records so we
don't really know but at least in mumbai
and karachi there was indiscriminate
firing on indians
unarmed indians
and it caused hundreds of deaths
now
the congress party
under the leadership of mr gandhi
condemned the uprising
they condemned the 1946
naval revolt against the british
the muslim league also condemned
the uprising of the
navy of the indian uh naval force
because
at that time these two parties were in
negotiations with the british
for a proper ceremonial handing over of
power
the british had made it clear that they
wanted to leave india they were not in a
position to manage india it was too
difficult too expensive they they were
bankrupt basically because of the war
they wanted to leave india
and the congress and the muslim league
were trying to get negotiate and get the
best deal possible the muslim league
wanted
a separate nation of pakistan the
congress wanted a handover of power to
themselves
and this revolution if it happened
it would
basically destroy their dreams the
partition would never have happened
the people of india would have
captured
independence
by force instead of it being handed over
on a platter
on british terms
so this was a very dangerous moment for
the congress party in the muslim league
their dreams were on the verge of being
shattered so mr gandhi condemned
this uprising mr uh
patel came to bombay
and he urged
the uh
the rebels to step down
and he assured them he gave them up an
assurance on behalf of the british that
none of them would be persecuted for
what they've done just please surrender
end this nonsense
and none of you will be persecuted so
these guys saw that there was no
political support apart from the
communists
strangely enough the communists
in 46 supported this revolt but the
congress party and the muslims muslim
league did not support it they condemned
it
so these guys they found that there was
no support from the main two political
parties
and after they were given assurances by
mr patel mr sardar by patel
that there would be there would be no
repercussions no persecution
then they all surrendered so it lasted
about a week or ten days or so at most
they surrendered to the british the
moment they surrendered they were all
arrested
imprisoned
and court-martialed
so the word that they were given was
immediately broken they were told there
would be no persecution no victimization
they were persecuted they were
imprisoned for months solitary
confinement terrible treatment they were
court-martialed and i don't know what
else happened to them after india got
its so-called independence
and pakistan also became independent
these
people who fought the british on behalf
of india they were not reinstated to
their naval positions
they were not compensated for the ill
treatment and the loss of salary and all
that and we don't even know what
happened to them
so this is how india and also pakistan
treats its patriots
so this is
basically what happened in 1946 it was a
very dangerous moment for the british
for the congress party and for the
muslim league it was a spark of hope for
india that we could grab independence on
our own terms by kicking the british out
but the congress party and the muslim
league ensured that this did not happen
and
but this
uh incident it it told the it uh taught
the british a very valuable lesson they
realized that they could not hang on to
india it was imperative for them to
quickly leave the country as quickly as
possible because otherwise there will be
widespread slaughter and every british
man woman and child would be wiped out
from the soil of india that became very
clear and that's why there was this
hasty
process of
of the
partition of the drawing redrawing of
the boundaries of of and all that and
about
15 months or so later 15 16 months later
we had the partition of india and the
so-called independence of india and
pakistan so this is the story of the
1946 naval mutiny i would highly
recommend you read about this because it
this is something that very few people
have written about this is a chapter of
history that has essentially the
historians have tried to bury it because
it kind of shows us the truth
about what could really have happened
what was possible and what the congress
and the muslim league did
for the sake of their personal benefit
because they wanted
power to be handed to them
instead of the people
reclaiming the power which was theirs so
that's what happened
bobby asks
how many questions
how long was afghanistan part of india
that's question number one
how long was tibet independent question
number two prior to islam what was the
culture like in this region that's
question number three
and question four is how do you
distinguish a major difference between
persia and india prior to islam
okay let's begin with the first question
how long was afghanistan part of india
afghanistan was always part of india
from the beginning of
the human occupation of the indian
subcontinent
until about about 500 years ago
right so the people of afghanistan in
india are the same i am talking about
the pashtuns the pashtuns are
essentially
an outgrowth of the overall northern
indian and western indian population
genetically culturally etc
linguistically they are part of the
indian
ethnic
continuum
religiously and culturally now it has
changed a lot but there are still these
layers below the surface of culture and
and all that which are still very much
indian they will not agree to what i am
saying they will say no we're not
indians fine that's your choice that's
fine but facts are facts facts don't
care about anyone's feelings so
afghanistan was part of india from the
beginning of time
beginning of human history or beginning
of the history of the indian
subcontinent up until about the
the turkic invasions of india
when afghanistan was forcibly islamized
the buddhist hindu culture was wiped out
smashed destroyed
cultural genocide
endemic genocide
and so on
kandahar essentially was the city of the
rajputs do you know that
the pashtuns and the rajputs are
essentially the same people
of course now things have changed like i
said and today in afghanistan you have
these different ethnicities the uzbeks
the tajiks the turkmens and the hazaras
and all that these are
ethnicities that came in from outside as
a consequence of the islamic
of the turkic invasions of india
so around 500 years or so ago
the basically the the region kind of
started seeing itself as a separate
political
or rather cultural ethnocultural entity
but until 500 years ago indians and
afghans fought together bled together
died together in resisting the turks
because despite the religious difference
we were still the same people so that is
about afghanistan
question two is how long was tibet
independent
well if you look at the history of tibet
it's about i would say around 2000 years
old or so when it
emerged as a separate
ethnocultural entity
so tibet was
always
independent
the independence
ended in 1955 when the chinese communist
party invaded and india under sri jawal
nehru aided the chinese communist party
by sending them supplies of rice and
other
food stuffs so that they were able to
survive and that's why the chinese were
able to occupy tibet
before that the chinese communist
party's uh rationale
for invading tibet is that tibet was
part of the chinese yuan dynasty's
territory
so that is what they said they said that
the chinese yuan dynasty had conquered
tibet
and that's why tibet should be part of
china that is the logic
here's the
here's the truth the yuan dynasty
was a mongol dynasty
its founder
was shiri ching is khan
so shri changes khan invaded and smashed
china to bits
right
his
son ogde khan
continued the process further and he uh
he subjugated the entirety of china
and sri augudey khan's son
shiri kublai khan was the first yuan
emperor of china and retrospectively he
said that his grandfather sri chingish
khan was the first emperor of the yuan
dynasty so this was a mongol dynasty
neither ching is khan nor ogdekhan nor
kublai khan nor any of their descendants
were chinese
they were mongols
and therefore this was a mongol dynasty
it was not a chinese dynasty it was a
conquest dynasty of china its
capital was beijing because shri kublai
khan decided that he will sit in beijing
and lord over china
now here's the relationship between
uh the yuan dynasty in tibet
the yuan dynasty
decided to
accept tibet as its protectorate
see the relationship between tibet and
the mongols was that of guru and
cheshire
teacher and student guru and shisha the
tibetans were the gurus the mongols were
the shishas the tibetans
taught they served as priests and
teachers of the mongols when it came to
indian culture
vajrayana buddhism and all that so the
mongols they adopted
tibetan buddhism the tibetan flavor of
buddhism as their official de facto
state religion and culture and they
employed
tibetan
monks sadhus priests etc as their
teachers as their gurus as their
priests
and in return they said that we will
extend our protection
to tibet we will ensure that tibet is
not uh does not come under anyone any
kind of threat so they accepted they
took tibet as a protectorate they never
sent their troops into tibet they never
conquered tibet
when sri chingis khan
conquered karakitai
which is to the north of jammu and
kashmir and when he conquered the quran
empire which is to the north west of
jammu and kashmir he went through tibet
on his expedition and while coming back
to china he again passed through tibet
he did not ever
try to invade conquer tibet he just
passed through it
so it tells you that there was no
question of a conquest of tibet so tibet
was always independent it was a
protectorate of the one dynasty which
was a non-chinese dynasty but the
chinese now said it was a chinese
dynasty because its capital was beijing
and that's why they
consider to bed to be a part of china
and that justifies their invasion and
occupation of tibet so tibet ceased to
be independent in 1955 only
before that it was always independent in
the 8th century they actually conquered
china
and sacked the then capital of china
which was not beijing at the time
i forget which city it was you can look
it up
right so the tibetans actually conquered
china in the 8th century that they were
a powerful military uh force at the time
then they became
more civilized they went the way of
india later on and
as a result we can see what happened so
that's the story of tibet uh prior to
islam what was the culture like in these
regions tibet was never islamic it is
still not islamic so
it's been the same it's been a buddhist
culture
they also have their indigenous born
religion which is very similar to
hinduism in buddhism right so it's today
they practice a syncretic form of
hinduism buddhism born etc hinduism
buddhism is essentially the same thing
like i have said many times
so that's their culture afghanistan the
culture was for thousands of years what
we call hinduism later it became a
different flavor of hinduism which is
buddhism
the uh the gory dynasty was a buddhist
dynasty then it became uh turkey-sized
it came under the influence of the
turkic invasions it got converted to
islam and then that's when the
conversion of
afghanistan to islam began then you had
the influx of various other ethnic
groups in afghanistan and today you have
this mixed bag in afghanistan where the
major
the majority ethnic group is the
pashtuns who are the true natives
of afghanistan of gandhar
and you have other ethnicities as well
the uzbeks the trajects the kyrgyz the
hazaras the turkmens
and not
so the culture in afghanistan was indian
culture
because when shwan zang the great
chinese monk came to india
the moment he reached bamiyan the
bamiyan valley he said thank god i have
finally reached india
so it tells you afghanistan was india
okay next question is how do you
distinguish a major difference between
persia and india prior to islam prior to
islam persia and india were
like cousins
uh i have spoken about this in previous
episodes the persians were the
descendants of the parshwa clan
of the rig vedic indians there was this
battle of ten kings i know you guys have
asked me many times i'll make a detailed
analysis of the battle of ten kings in a
separate video so in the battle of ten
kings
one of the clans the clans that was
expelled out of india was the parshwa
clan
so these guys went westwards
and they settled in the region which is
now named after the them
the parshwa people settled in a region
which
came to be known as persia so it is
named after this clan the parshwa clan
right so these were
rigvedic people
they they practiced rigvedic culture and
religion later on this
new religion emerged zoroastrianism
which emerged about three three and a
half thousand years ago so it's its
origins are
still uh
shrouded in obscurity we don't know
exactly when this individual shri
zoroaster lived his name was
ustra yellow camel or golden camel
uh that's that's what it means in
sanskrit zarat
yellow camel
so zarathustra died in the city of
bahalik bulk in afghanistan
he
uh was the first prophet
of a revealed religion
zoroastrianism so zoroastrianism was
essentially in a kind of inversion of
hinduism they was became kind of evil
asuras became kind of good that sort of
thing sort of inversion it was still a
polytheistic religion it was not a
monotheistic religion this is an
enormous misconception that people have
that zoroastrianism is a monotheistic
religion that is utter nonsense it was a
polytheistic religion it was very much
a post-vedic religion much of the
ritualism and all was still retained in
zoroastrianism the yaknas became yasnas
uh
and so on and so forth you know the soma
ritual still continued viritra han
became
virtu indra he became considered to be
kind of evil there
the
the destruction of the
evil
serpent
is also reflected in persian mythology
and all that so it is much the same even
in zoroastrianism
so
in the language the old persian language
was kind of a dialect
an upper british dialect of sanskrit the
vocabulary and grammar was exactly the
same the pronunciations were slightly
different
and later on as time evolved and as time
went by things slightly diverged but
indians and persians were still very
much neighbors very much
brothers or at least cousins
until the arabic invasion of persia
which happened like ridiculously fast in
a couple of decades the entire religion
and culture of persia had changed
the same could not happen in india so
that's that's the difference between
india and persia prior to the advent of
islam in persia
so i hope that answers this question
a.s patel
asks is it true that barbara the sultan
of kabul
was descended from timur on his mother's
side and ching is khan on his father's
side so this is a myth it's an entire
complete fabrication
babar was a turk he was born in the city
of andhijan
in uzbekistan
right he was born there then there were
some problems in succession and all so
he decided to invade northern india he
kind of succeeded etc that's a story now
his story his mythological tale is that
his mother was a descendant of timur the
great
monster
and his father was descended from
chingis the great mongol
now this is a claim that he made
it's a claim do we have evidence of it
we have
zero evidence of this claim
see if you want to become a great ruler
it helps
this story behind you that i am the
dissident of two great conquerors
it helps it gives you more legitimacy
so it is
quite common for these upstart rulers to
claim descent
from great historical figures
so babar claimed that he is he was
descended from
timur on one side and uh from chingus on
the other side there is zero zero point
zero evidence of this claim it is merely
a claim a claim that is made without
evidence can be dismissed without
evidence so end of story
gaurav says obama's parents were from
kenya but he was an american born and
became u.s president outstanding man he
was not called an invader
akbar was indian born so how can he be
an invader
okay wonderful question okay look gaurav
your logic makes sense my question is
this
how old is the united states of america
it is less than 250 years old
how old is india
it is thousands of years old do we need
to ape
this new upstart nation that is already
crumbling
do we need to aid them or should we have
our own standards of whom we define as
our citizens and whom we define as
outsiders
there are two concepts of citizenships
of citizenship
one is
solely the other is jus sanguinis
you solely is the right
of citizenship if you're born on a
nation's soil
sanguines is
you get the right to be citizen if you
are descended if you sanguines means
blood
if you have descent by blood
in a nation
babur had no indian blood
so if he was born in i mean
we're talking about akbar right akbar
did not have indian blood
he was a turk
being born on indian soil
doesn't make him an indian
according to
sanguinis
and today in 21st century india
the nation of india does not recognize
jews solely
citizenship by birth india does not
recognize citizenship by birth
so according to the indian modern
definition of citizenship akbar was not
a citizen of india
and according to
our age-old traditions
you can be born in this country it
doesn't make you a citizen you have to
be
invested in the culture
of the country
dna doesn't matter i mean dna does
matter
to some extent this is not a dna
question it's about it's about
being born on the soil so akbar was born
in india
but was he indian did was he indian by
culture
did he practice indian culture did he
speak in indian language
he did not
he his actions
were
anti-indian culture he tried to promote
his foreign culture in india so how does
it make him an indian he's
a person born in india to foreigner
parents who was trying to promote and
spread a foreign culture in india
so that doesn't make him an indian that
makes him an innovator kaneshka was a
descendant of foreigners the great king
kanishka he spent his life
promoting indian culture and promoting
the indian national interest and
civilizational interest
he spread indian culture far and wide
across asia
he expanded in india's military with
india's cultural civilizational and
economic and military footprint
by waging vigorous military campaigns
far beyond india's present geographical
boundaries
so that is a true indian
akbar did the opposite
he waged war within india to stamp out
indian culture
despite whatever your textbooks have
taught you about him about him being a
secular king and all that nonsense
so akbar was a foreigner
he was not indian by any means you can
keep believing it some of you i mean
that's your choice my view is very clear
he was not indian by any by any
definition whatsoever
sri rang says asks why did the shia
suffer with
king help the sunni humayun
that's an excellent question right i
think in one of the previous videos i
spoke about humayun and
the influence how did the how did the
so-called mughals that these turks adopt
persian as their official court language
and the
answer was that it's because of the
influence of the safavid uh king
of persia tamas
who sent a bunch of
a large number of officials and
bureaucrats with humayun on his attempt
to reconquer india
and humayun succeeded and he employed
all these persian speaking people as his
staff and that's how this this entire
process began
so why did this shia king
the the the
this guy thomas why did he help the
sunni humayun that's an excellent
question so when the
indigenous native
uh sher shasuri defeated humayun and
expelled him from india
humayun went westwards
and he sought refuge in neighboring
persia in iran their king was
he was a shia
humayun like you said was a sunni turk
so why did this shia guy help this sunni
turk
well the answer is surprising
he
compelled humayun to convert to shia
islam
so humayun converted to shia islam in
order to
acquire an
alliance and and acquire ref and gain
refuge in the court of this
iranian
king
and it is only after humayun converted
to shia islam
that the hamas agreed to help him
on his attempt in his attempt to
reconquer this lost uh
portion of northern india
and that's the story so later on when
humayun re-conquered that part of india
delhi in northern india i think he may
have reconverted to shia islam or
something or to sunni islam
because we know that the uh
these mughals the so-called mughals were
uh shia muslims so i think humayun must
have reconverted
to sunni there were sunni muslims he
must have reconverted to sunni islam
it's kind of confusing shia sunni
but yes the mughals were sunni
muslims aurangzeb was sunni
so i think after the reconquest of
northern india humayun reconverted
to sunni islam from shia islam
so that is the story that is why tahamas
the king the shah of iran agreed to help
humayun because he first
made humayun convert to shia islam
para yotis yanapulos says it's an
oversimplification also to put all on
the same basket and say they were no
different
alexander brought with him greek city
architects in general
along with gymnasiums museums sports
economic advancements all the
fascinating fantastic greek culture
and advancement of the times
he had he offered it to be freely shared
he is maybe the only one who built more
cities than he raised
so what uh mr yanupolos is saying is
that
alexander the macedonian was actually a
very good generous benevolent king he
conquered to enrich the conquered
peoples with greek culture and greek
architecture and economics and sports
and museums
and advancements because these conquered
people were all backward right they did
not have any advancements that the
greeks had
so alexander conquered in order to
bring these people out of their
backwardness and offer all these
fantastic european advancements to them
so let us take a look at
alexander the macedonians exploits
shall we
let me share my screen with you my
friends
let's talk about alexander
right
just a minute let me remove this
here we are
so this is uh in the beginning this this
is a book called the book's name is the
madness of alexander the great and the
myth of military genius the author is
richard gabriel note it down purchase
the book if you
can now what does it say here
this is in the beginning of alexander's
career as a tyrant
so he conquered the city of tyre in
lebanon
lebanon is in the eastern mediterranean
okay so when the macedonians finally bro
broke through the fortifications and
entered the city the slaughter was
terrible for the macedonians went to
work with savage ferocity some eight
thousand were killed and thirty 000 men
women and children were
sold into slavery
as a final outrage alexander crucified
all the men of military age these were
no less than
2 000.
so i don't see any museums or culture or
advancements
being proffered to the people of tyree
here
you have eight thousand killed thirty
thousand men women and children enslaved
and two thousand men crucified what sort
of barbarian was he let's look further
at shri alexander
the fact that alexander took personal
pleasure in the torture and death of
betis bethis was a
persian general
it suggests the presence of a sadistic
streak in his personality which would
make itself evident numerous times in
the future
later alexander personally witnessed the
torture of philotas
ordered the stoning of suspected
conspirators crucified thousands of
captives and occasionally murdered or
tortured victims himself
what a nice person he was
these are greek advancements i suppose
let's see some more
brahmanas in this the indus valley
campaign
alexander sailed down the indus river
attacking and slaughtering tribes as he
went
to no apparent military purpose except
perhaps to vent his frustrations for
having to bring his indian adventure to
an end he ravaged the kingdom of sambos
enslaved the people of the population of
most of the cities and later destroyed
the cities
he then crucified the king oh nice
the brahmin priests were
etc the brahmins urged resistance
and alexander took it personally
executing all the priests and the
families he could get his hands on
citing
kleitarkas as their source courteous and
diadora say that in this campaign
against the indian tribes alexander
killed 80 000 indians in this region and
captured many others
right
so uh for whatever reasons alexander
exterminated thousands of brahmin
priests when he could not kill them in
large numbers he seems to have preferred
hanging them individually
what a great man of culture
let's look here the victory over porous
had no strategic effect except to unify
the indians on the other side of the
river to rally and prepare to fight
alexander together confronted with this
opposition in the mutiny of his troops
alexander was forced to abandon his
campaign
the transit down the indus river so
alexander perpetrate one slaughter after
another
if alexander thought his brutality would
induce would reduce resistance he was
grossly mistaken
right so he enjoyed
it must be born in mind that alexander
did not just order these atrocities to
be committed he was an enthusiastic
participant in them he enjoyed wading
into the slaughter almost as if he could
not stop himself his passion for glory
was such that he did not have the
strength of mind
to consider his own safety etc
alexander's killing was a bloody
business indeed
where he could see the fear in his
victims eyes and all that
so this is the kind of individual mr
alexander was alexander
uh alexander the great
macedonian
so i failed to
understand
what was this
greek culture and advancements that he
brought to these people whether it is
entire whether it is in persia whether
it was in the western fringes of india
there was no gymnasiums or museums or
sports
or economic advancements or greek
culture or advancement
it was
barbarism
which seems to be a hallmark of the
western cultures unfortunately
so that is all mr alexander brought
to whether to whatever region he invaded
and it is only fitting that he met his
end in india
he fought porus the greeks claimed that
he defeated porus which seems to be an
absolute lie of fabrication
what actually happened was that he was
defeated in india he was grievously
wounded he limped back to babylon where
he died from his wounds so it is a
fitting end to one of the worst
barbarians in human history
aditya says this is not related to
indian history but i am curious to know
uh how did egypt
north africa and middle east get so rich
despite being a barren land
and nobody needed oil in those days
well this is uh this is a belief lots
and lots of people have that egypt north
africa the middle east were
extraordinarily rich in the past the
roman empire was the richest empire of
all time and india is insignificant
let me again share my screen
okay
so this is
uh a screenshot from
angus medicine's
great work on the economic history of
the world
so angus medicine i think he's an
american economist
had an indian economist
brought this out he would have been
immediately uh
marginalized and he would not have been
taken seriously but this is an american
economist
and this is the
uh gold standard when it comes to the
economic history of the world okay so
this is the economic history of the
world over the past two thousand years
if you look here it's the year one the
year thousand fifteen hundred et cetera
this is the year 2003. so this is the
gdp of the worlds of various regions
across time to according to this
gentleman's
calculations so let's take a look at
india's gdp
okay
so uh india's gdp in the year 180 was 33
33 billion us dollars in in today's
money in 1990
india's gdp in the year one was 33
billion u.s dollars of 1990 us dollars
let's compare that with western west
asia
west asia's gdp was 10
10 billion one-third of that of india
right let's look at uh the gdp of where
is africa africa's gdp was eight billion
so it is one-fourth of india's gdp less
than one-fourth
west asia's gdp was less than half less
than a third of india's gdp
right
if you look at the year 1000 you have
very similar numbers africa is
even if you look at let's say
the entirety of europe
in the year one it is 14 billion
us dollars which is less than half of
india's gdp the entirety of europe
western europe
its entire gdp taken together which
includes the roman empire by the way
is less than half of india's gdp
i think this puts things in perspective
that india's gdp was always enormous
india was the economic not just
superpower it was a hyper power in the
world and actually these calculations
they are not very accurate there are
certain oversimplifications i believe
india's gdp was even higher than what is
put out here and yet even these
very conservative figures tell you very
clearly that india dwarfed the rest of
the world when it came to economic uh to
its economic power to its the size of
its economy right whether it's africa
whether it's egypt whether it's west
asia whether it's northern europe
whether it's the roman empire they were
all dwarfed
by india's gdp if you look at if you
read india history textbooks they talk
about the roman empire as the greatest
empire the world has ever seen nothing
has ever come close to it in size except
perhaps egypt in the ancient world and
yet these figures show you
that these were insignificant
in comparison with india
so let us disabuse ourselves of these uh
myths
that egypt north africa middle east rome
etc were so rich
they were rich to some extent because of
their imperialistic practices egypt was
an empire they did conquer other
kingdoms they plundered them and that's
how they became rich they had the
fertile nile valley which was great for
agriculture so that was also a source of
income
they had mining and other things so
these were some sources of income for
them that's how they were able to build
up some
uh
percentage of the world's gdp rome was
all about conquest of destroying other
cultures destroying and
perpetrating genocide and
extracting the wealth out of whether it
is hispania which is spain or the
gaulish country which is france etc
whether it's from judea which is present
in palestine israel whether it's north
africa they extracted and plundered and
that's how rome became rich and yet its
gdp is a fraction its gdp was a fraction
of india's gdp and india's gdp
was built up without ever conquering a
foreign country so that's the difference
okay two questions one is from aman
singh if the british would have not come
would we still be under the control of
the turks
naman asks had the british not come to
india we would still be slaves of the
mughals so this is a sentiment i see all
the time
so people believe that the british saved
us we everyone agrees i i know that the
british rule was bad for india the
british occupation was terrible for
india and yet it saved us from the turks
this is what everybody believes
let me once again
share my screen
let's take a look at this
this is the high tide of the maratha
empire july 1759
do you see any green in this
do you see any mughal empire in this the
mughal empire was a turkic empire
this was the situation in india
in july 1759 this is the high tide of
the maratha empire they had annihilated
the mughal empire they had destroyed it
they had taken over
much of india
the whole of western india much of
central india the heartland of india
much of northern india all the way up to
parts of afghanistan
right
this was the maratha empire it is this
empire that the british defeated in
three
i think it was three anglo-maratha wars
so the british
defeated the marathas
not the turks the marathas had destroyed
the turks the marathas had
they had created hinduism in india
they had recreated
a hindu empire in india
that's what the british destroyed they
did not destroy the turkic empire they
destroyed the hindu maratha empire
so had it not been for the british
india would have been a hindu russia
today that's what everyone asked me is
hindu russia possible well it was
possible it actually happened and that's
what the british destroyed they
introduced what we now call secularism
all right my friends so that's what
happened
sujay says
can you please explain how the himalayas
were formed
and what is the importance of this
mountain range for the subcontinent or
the entire world
so the himalayas were formed because of
tectonic activity
see
let me do i have a map here i do have a
map just a second let me share the map
with you
um
just a minute
okay here is the map
this is our planet
as you can see
this here is india so what happens is
that this planet of ours
it uh if you look at the cross section
of the planet
you have a very thin solid crust
which is the upper one or two percent of
the earth okay
and inside you have a
layer of magma which is molten rock and
if you go deeper you have the core of
the earth which is made up of molten
metal and then you have a solid metal
inner core of the earth
so this magma this layer of magma
which is below the mantle of the earth
and the mantle is below the crust this
magma is a liquid it is liquid rock it
flows inside the earth and this
activity this flowing activity of the
magma causes what is known as tectonic
activity of the earth's crust so you
have portion of the earth various
portions of the earth's crust that move
over time
very slowly but they do move and these
movements cause the
changes in the structure of the
continents of the earth so there was a
time when all the continents of the
earth were united in one in one super
continent called pangaea and then they
drifted they drifted away
and this is the structure that we have
today
so about 60 uh
how long ago was this about 100 million
years ago or so
india
the peninsular part of india was
attached to
southern southeastern
africa
so if you look at madagascar here you
can see that the shape of madagascar
kind of fits here like a jigsaw puzzle
in the eastern coast of africa
and if you see the shape of this
peninsular part of india that also kind
of fits into this into this shape here
in the southern part of africa
so madagascar and india were attached to
africa and because of tectonic activity
the peninsula part of india was thrown
out was expelled from africa and it shot
across the indian ocean
and it collided into the eurasian land
mass
and this collision
which happened at a very slow rate and
yet it was produced by immense forces
from within the earth
so this collision
between the indian subcontinental land
mass and the eurasian landmass this
cataclysmic collision
pushed the himalayas upwards
and that's how the himalayas were born
and if you go to the himalayas if you
climb up the himalayas if you climb
several thousand meters up you will
still find fossils of fish several
thousand meters above sea level because
that region was once under water it was
once an ocean
and it was expelled up
because of the
uh collision between the between the
indian landmass and the eurasian
landmass between these two tectonic
plates so that's how the himalayas were
formed let me show you a different image
just a second
let me show a different image
okay if you see this it makes it a
little more clear
you can kind of
see
the
you can uh this is this is a map of the
ocean floor you can kind of see the
under under ocean structure of the
planet if all the water is removed and
you can kind of see the kind of movement
which
which took place
so it gives you a better idea of how
these uh
pieces of the jigsaw puzzle fit together
once upon a time about 100 million years
ago
so that is that kind of illustrates the
kind of tectonic activity that took
place over the eons and that is how the
himalayan mountain range was formed up
in the north
of
india
right
okay next question
uh is it true that vasco da gama was was
escorted to india by a gujarati
merchant
so vascular gamma was a portuguese
sailor
who was looking for india
in the 15th century i believe the
ottomans
captured turkey they captured
constantinople and they cut off
the land route between europe and india
the europeans used to trade with india
for various
various precious things like gold
actually they did not trade for gold
they traded for
they imported spices from india and
various textiles and other things which
were all considered to be luxury items
in europe and in return they sent gold
to india and that's why india is the
world's used to be the world's
go the world's gold store house india
was the gold rich country in the world
even today it is to some extent
so the europeans were
dependent on these luxury items from
india they priced these and valued these
items very much spices textiles and all
these finished products
so when the ottomans when the turks
captured anatolia and
greece parts of greece etc they cut off
the trade routes between europe and
india and that's why people like
columbus basketball they started looking
for alternative routes to reach india so
columbus went east he went westwards he
tried to cross the atlantic he stumbled
into america he thought it was india
vasquez decided to
let me show the map
the map once again
okay where is the map
so vasco de gama
decided
to move out of portugal which is here as
you can see this is portugal
he went southwards
he went around africa
around the cape of good hope
and he was looking for india
so he came across this kingdom of
malindi
malindi is here
in kenya
and i believe that's i think it's
somewhere here that he met an indian
merchant
because indians
lived they they had been living in
eastern africa for
centuries or maybe thousands of years
and they used to trade there
so it was mostly gujaratis and maybe
even people from southern india kerala
etc who used to live in eastern africa
and trade there were traders and all
that so many of them lived there for
generations
so he came across some indians there i
believe it was one of these indians who
escorted vasco de gama to india to
kerala now we are not sure about the uh
about the identity of this person
who
escorted vasco de gama
to to india
maybe it was a gujarati person maybe it
was uh somebody from kerala we don't
really know we don't know who it was
so
and the records i mean
we don't have records of exactly who the
person was so there is a great deal of
speculation some historians have
speculated that the person was a
gujarati merchant
some people think it was somebody from
kerala or southern india we're not sure
what we know is that he
most likely met this person
in malindi
in the kingdom of the in the sultanate
of malindi and this is an image
of vascular gamma meeting the sultan of
malindi
and you can see how the europeans have
painted it like vasco de gama is some
great
god like figure and these
these are the these the sultan is like a
servant to him
and as you can see there's an indian
person over here who's holding
this uh
umbrella umbrella umbrella-like thing
so this is a depiction of a european
depiction of vascular gamma meeting upon
beating the sultan of malindi and
meeting an indian person
the dress of the indian person looks
like he's from uh gujarat it's a kind of
saurashtrian kind of dress it does look
like that
this is a european depiction of bhaskar
gama
meeting the king
in
what place was it calicut the calicut
yeah
so it once again there you can see the
depiction it shows vascular gamma like a
heroic figure
and the indian says
inferior kind of people so that's the
kind of depictions racist depictions you
have
you had in europe and you still have
them
of indians and all non-european people
so that is what we know that is how the
europeans have depicted it we don't
really know the identity of the person
who brought moscow the government to
india it could quite likely have been
somebody from gujarat but we are not 100
sure of that
subhashi says a recent study done by
historians on decoding the seals of the
indus valley civilization they said that
the harappan people used to speak a
proto-dravidian language whatever that
means
thereby reinforcing their aryan
migration invasion tourism picnic theory
what's my thoughts on this
listen um
there have been many claims by various
people to have decoded
the harappan the so-called harappan
script or the indus valley script or the
saraswati script
none of these claims has been
corroborated
none of these claims has been proven
there was this individual called iran
mahadevan
who
wrote a book about this he said he had
decoded the script and
he wrote a book about this with his
so-called decoding with his translation
of the script which was all make believe
he did not ever
communicate by what means he came across
this translation or this decoding of the
script he simply said this symbol means
this in tamil this symbol means this in
tamil but how did you make this up
what's the logic behind it what's the
thought process there has to be some
logic behind a decoding of a language or
a script
and he failed to provide that
and therefore his his claim is
completely false is completely unproven
there are some people especially the
aryan invasion theorists who treat
hirawati mahatma as a god may the gods
have mercy on his on his
soul because he has passed away but his
uh
his work is basically nonsense okay so
first of all iran mahadeva's
decoding of the script is
completely incorrect and secondly there
have been many people who have claimed
that it is a dravidian script or
whatever that means like you say but
there is no proof of that
people make claims without any proof
show me the proof
show us the proof it has to be proof
that stands up to scrutiny
well nobody has ever produced any screw
any proof that can stand up to scrutiny
nobody has pro
produced
a decipherment of the script that
actually stands up to scrutiny nobody
and therefore as of today we don't know
what this script was
um we don't know what language it
encoded
so as of today both options are still
open whether it was a so-called
dravidian
language that it
was meant to communicate or whether it
was a
what they call an indo-aryan language
most likely sanskrit my
belief
it is still a belief because it's my
hypothesis is that it was
a form of sanskrit pre-classical
sanskrit most likely
vedic or or post-vedic sanskrit that is
my hypothesis i also still don't have
any evidence for it but that's what i
believe
now these claims have never been proven
so what needs to be done is we need to
invest the well we means the government
needs to invest in deciphering the
script
we need to use technology to do this we
have machine learning and algorithms and
not
i mean they the in the west they have
been doing they have been using machine
learning artificial intelligence to
decode in real time egyptian
hieroglyphics
right
so we can do that we can try and do the
same for the so-called harappan script
and try and see what language it fits
best
whether it is proto-tamil or or
rig vedic sanskrit or whatever it is
so that needs to happen until that
happens there is no way of saying
what language this script was meant to
communicate
harshit asks since the indus valley
civilization was spread across a very
large area is there any evidence which
shows that the people spoke multiple
languages that's a very nice question
very interesting questions question but
uh
as of today we don't have any evidence
to show that the people spoke multiple
languages
we see kind of a uniformity of culture
we see standardization across this
entire
vast geographical region the entire
suburbs indo region
and
regions beyond that i mean the harappan
sites have been found all the way up to
southern afghanistan the entirety of
pakistan balochistan
kashmir
punjab aryana western uttar pradesh the
entirety of gujarat
and parts of northern maharashtra that's
an enormous geographical region it is
bigger than than
egypt and mesopotamia put together it's
an enormous region and you see
standardization across the entire region
the same weights and measures the same
kind of
figurines and same kind of pottery same
kind of uh
geometrical and other kind of drawings
you see that this was one single
overarching culture
and you had the same standardization of
weights and measures and everything so
it was essentially whether it was
multiple kingdoms multiple city-states
or one single empire we don't know for
sure
there is no evidence of any royal
palaces or anything in the government
structure so it seems to be some kind of
democracy may have existed
but
we don't have evidence for multiple
languages from what we know thus far we
have excavated less than one percent of
the archaeological sites so there is
a huge deal still that we don't know
about this this uh era of our
ancient history so from what we have
today there is no evidence that people
spoke multiple languages but it's
possible that they did that they did we
just need to
explore and excavate more
yash
asks subhash chandra bose and
pandit jawala nehru were close friends
or enemies
well subhashindra bose and shiri nehru
were by no means close friends
they were competitors they were rivals
the great mr nehru was
you could say he was
he was under the wing of uh the great mr
mohandas gandhi
the
the uh
father of the nation supposedly right
so mr nehru was in mr gandhi's camp
right and subhash chandra bose was kind
of a polarizing figure it was kind of a
maverick
uh
he
had he had his own brand of politicians
he had his own ideas which were very
much at odds with what gandhi
sought for india so vahchandra bose was
in
he demanded complete independence from
the british gandhi was happy with
dominion status
you know that sort of thing so watching
the bose was very much open to a violent
overthrow of the british gandhi was
against violence by any means
so vahchandra bose was a very popular
figure
he was a huge threat for gandhi
for mr gandhi when mr gandhi came to
india from south africa
he overnight became the superstar in the
congress party but then a new star
emerged sabas chandra bose
and i think it was in 1930 something
that mr bose actually became the
president of the congress party he was
elected as the president
and it was mr mohandas gandhi
who engineered a political coup
and
overthrew subhashan rabos from the
congress party from the presidency of
the congress party and he appointed some
puppet guy
as the president of the
congress party
so that's what mr gandhi did
he engineered a political coup
to overthrow sebastian rabos and mr
nehru mr said mr nehru was never a great
leader a great politician a great
anything
mr nehru i regret to say was a very
mediocre
individual
right they respected shiri naruji
so
mr nero was somebody who was suspicious
who was uh
who had this inferiority complex
especially when it came to a genuine
star like subhash in the rabos so they
were never friends never they were never
ever friends
and
after um there is this alleged letter
that mr nero
wrote in 1946
to the then prime minister of the united
kingdom clement atlee
uh
urging mr atlee to have subhashin rabos
arrested in the soviet union
because he had come to know mr nero had
come to know that zabashan rabos had
crossed over into the soviet union's
territory so it is alleged there is this
alleged letter that shows that uh mr
nehru wrote to clement atlee calling
subhashin the bose of war criminal and
urging the uk prime minister to have to
take some action
against sebastian rabos
now many people claim this letter is
fake many people say it's true
until the government releases all the
records we will not know for sure but it
is well known that mr nehru did not like
sabach in the rebels he was an enemy of
subachi rabos
after mr bose's alleged death it is also
well known that after india's
independence nehru
shireen aruji
had spied had spied upon so watching the
bose's family for many years
so it's clear that they were never close
friends of or or friends of any kind
they were political rivals mr nehru
resented subachin rabosa's brilliance
and
so watching the bose was everything he
was basically the polar opposite of
nehru he was a genuine leader
he was a man who inspired devotion
in the people
he was a man for whom people gave their
lives
when fighting for the indian national
army he was a man who put his life on
the line subachin the rabos he was a man
who put his reputation on the line for
the sake of his country he was willing
to ally with the japanese and with
hitler in order to defeat the british
so he put his entire reputation on the
line for the sake of his country he did
not care if his reputation was turned
into dust
as long as he was able to free his
country
mr nehru was the opposite of that
and therefore
they were never close friends there were
enemies there were rivals mr nehru
well hate is a very strong word but he
i would say disliked mr subhash and
there was so that is the story
nita asks you said that dalits or lower
caste got education in ancient india but
what about karna in the mahabharat he
was denied education and why is there
caste divided et cetera aditya says if
the ancient indian education system
allows students of every caste etcetera
and gender to study then why did guru
drona not teach karna
yeah this question i get a lot they also
talk about mr iklovia who was also
denied education
training etc by
the guru dronacharya
okay good question very good question
this needs to be addressed so i'm going
to address this to address it today
imagine this scene
imagine this scene in england in ancient
england during the
during the tudor era of england during
the reign of henry viii or any ancient
king of england imagine this scene
you have
a teacher of martial arts
who is instructing the royal princes of
england
in archery and sword fighting
so this is a teacher of martial arts who
is employed by the king of england
to teach the princes
the martial arts archery and sword
fighting
so he's doing this he's instructing
these princes
and some bloody commoner
a son of a farmer or a son of a peasant
turns up
and says you need to teach me too
i demand that you teach me archery and
sword fighting and horse riding
how would he be treated
how would this son of a farmer
be treated if he turned up
went to the teacher of the princes and
said teach me sword fighting and archery
what would happen to him he would be
thrown out immediately
and he would be given a hundred lashes
of the whip if he was lucky
maybe he would be beheaded
for his impertinence
right so is there any caste divide in
this
do you see anything wrong with what
happens here
is the teacher of the princes the royal
instructor
under any obligation
to offer his expertise and and
instructions to anybody who turns up
no obviously not the same happened in
the mahabharata guru nacharya he was the
teacher of the royal princes
he was a martial arts teacher he taught
them martial arts sword fighting archery
horse riding and all that
his duty was to instruct the royal
princes in the martial arts
his duty was not to teach any tom dick
or harry who turned up and said teach me
too
right
but guru duronacharya was not the only
guru in the country
there were thousands of other gurus who
could also teach these things
so it was nothing to do with karna's
caste or whatever it is or equal obvious
caste
it was about them not being royals
karna was the son of what was it
charioteer or whatever
apparently and iklavi was also he was
not there was no
caste device those were dalits or
shudras or whatever that was they were
simply not royal princes and that's
where that's why they were denied by
nacharya it had nothing to do with caste
you cannot go to the teacher of the
princes of the of the royalty and say
teach me too it just doesn't work
anywhere in the world
so this has nothing to do with the
so-called caste divide i hope that makes
it clear
harish asks what benefit did rajiv
gandhi government foresee by sending the
ipk of the indian peacekeeping force
into sri lanka and getting involved in
the war with the ltte
what did we finally achieve
because of this
etc
okay so the ipkf the indian peacekeeping
force was sent into sri lanka by rajiv
gandhi with the
with the approval of the sri lankan
government
i think it was in 1987
and this was at the height of the
militancy the
terrorist outfit lt sorry ltte was
in possession of northern sri lanka and
there was a civil war going on
so
the indian government under sri rajiv
gandhi sent an indian peacekeeping force
into sri lanka
now as we know
this chapter of history is called
india's vietnam
it was a military disaster for india
india did not achieve anything through
this military operation
india was india did not defeat the ltd
india did not end the civil war and
there were many indian soldiers
who died
in this
in as a result of this operation so what
went wrong is the question it went wrong
it was a botched operation
in uh in the year
uh
which year was it 1990 i think
we brought the soldiers back to india so
it was
not a good
um
good thing for india right it wasn't we
did not cover ourselves in glory it was
not the fault of the indian armed forces
it was the fault of the political class
it was the fault of the indian
leadership let me explain why
when you
sent send the army
into a military operation
you need to give them a very clear
time-bound military objective go there
get in there do this job and get out in
this much time
that has that is the best
uh
kind of order you can give to an army
go to this uh territory
get this work done
wipe out this these insurgents
terrorists whatever and get out in this
much time you have this much time so the
orders have to be very specific
and they have to be time-bound
and you cannot tie the army's arms
behind their back
what happened was that the indian army
was not given any any military objective
they were they were simply asked to go
and sit there in sri lanka
go and sit there
you are not allowed to do this not
allowed to do that stay out of
civilian areas don't use heavy weapons
don't do this don't do that
and there was no military objective
the army was used like a police force
the army never does well when it is
employed like a police force the army
does well
when you are given a clear strategic or
tactical objective a time-bound
objective
so the army's indian army the ipkf's
hands were tied behind their backs they
were not allowed to use heavy weapons
they were not allowed to fight in
civilian areas even though the ltd did
that they were not given a time-bound
objective
if they had been told you have three
months to defeat the ltt do whatever you
need to do they would have won in less
than three three months
but they were not given any such
objective they were used like a police
force they had no clear objectives they
had no time bound frame time frame in
their hands were tied behind their backs
and that is why the ipkf
and the operation ended in a debacle for
india it was not the fault of the indian
armed forces it was entirely the fault
of the indian leadership of the time
they crippled and hobbled the indian
army and ensured
that it ended up as a disaster so that
in short is the
unfortunate
story of the ipkf
we could have finished this entire
matter in three months
if we had been if the indian army had
been
given all liberty you know so that's
what happened
saurabh asks it seems you are blocking
my comments
kindly read the this some article my
question to you is why a genetic north
indian is so different from a genetic
south indian if they come from the same
indian subcontinent
why does the rocky gory skeleton not
have the y haplotype marker r1a1
okay first of all saurabh i am not
blocking your comments if i had blocked
your comments i would not be showing
this
what happens is that the youtube
algorithm sometimes deletes comments
automatically autonomously based on
certain words that you may or may not
use
or certain other keywords that only it
understands i don't know what goes on in
the mind of the algorithm i don't know
many people have complained even during
the book giveaway that their comments
were getting deleted
unfortunately there's nothing i can do
about it okay so i'm not blocking your
comments that's part one
now your i don't know what that
article is about
but i am
well versed with this
particular question
so your question is that why is a
genetic north indian so different from a
genetic south indian what absolute
nonsense
i can show you result after result in
the most prestigious scientific journals
in the world nature for example google
it
i will not spoon feed you you need to do
a little bit of homework google it
google india's genetics in
and search in the journal nature
you will see study after study which
demonstrates that there is no difference
genetic difference between people of
northern india and people of southern
india even the people of afghanistan
even the people of bangladesh even the
people of sri lanka even the people of
the maldives
these days these people
in the west
who are trying to keep the aryan tourism
theory alive they have come up with a
new classification
ancestral north indians and ancestral
south indians
that is a fake made-up thing
if you look at the surface
there is no real difference
right
so
the genetics are much the same there is
a great deal of very variance and
variety and diversity in india's
population genetically india has the
highest amount of genetic diversity
outside of africa
and yet
india's population is genetically very
uniform so within this uniformity you
have an enormous amount of diversity
so it looks like there's a great deal of
diversity
and yet it is one
single ethnic continuum one single
genetic continuum
so you need to do a little bit of your
own research i will not show everything
here because if i try and dig up all the
all the references i'll spend another
two hours doing that so that's point
number one indians are the same
north indian south indians genetically
much the same
muthaya murali there and imran khan
genetically much the same whether you
realize it or not that's point number
one question number two you've asked is
why does does the rakigiri skeleton not
have the y haplotype marker r1a1
well you see my friend
yeah you are right
the rakigiri skeleton
does not have
the y haplotype marker i r1a1
it's because my friends the raker
skeleton is a female
i regret to say that females do not
carry the y chromosome
the females carry the x x
two x chromosomes
males carry an x chromosome and a y
chromosome so whenever you find a female
skeleton from any time period you will
never find any
why
genetic lineages
because why chromosomal
haplogroups are patrilineal haplogroups
they are passed from father to son
and they are absent in females the iraqi
grey skeleton is that of a female
they were able to extract dna only from
one skeleton
which was the skeleton of a female and
therefore the male
patrilineal
lineage is absent
in that skeleton
that's your answer
i hope
it makes sense
vikram asks could you please uh say give
some information about the saurashtra
region who are the subrasis people
see saurashtra let's uh
take a look at the map
where is the map
just a second
okay
here is the map so savarashtra so this
is the uh
this is india let's zoom in zoom in zoom
in zoom in
now in the west of india we have gujarat
gujarat looks like a face a person's
face
and the jaw
the
jaw part of the face is savarashtra it's
a peninsula it is called savarashtra
so this is the region of the swarastra
people are the people of who are native
to this region it's a very ancient
region
it's a very ancient people it was the it
was part of the
harappan heartland you have many harappa
sites in sabrashtra
lothal
dolavira and many more many more
and
in the
there were many
there were lots of foreign influences in
the region this region for example you
have the city called uh
there's this town
in saurashtra where is it where is it
where is it where is it
where is junagadh
i seem to be missing jungkook somewhere
looks like my geography of this region
isn't very good
let's search for junagadh
here it is this is
so the city of junagadh was once called
yavanagad yonagard or yavangat which
means the city of the greeks
of the yavana of the yavana people
so this so there was a significant
indo-greek
uh
influence at one point in time about two
thousand two hundred years ago in
western india it was also present in
saurashtra
this town junagad was apparently once an
indo-greek enclave of sorts
later on you had skitian influences in
those ketane influences in this region
you had the
various dynasties and kings and all that
saurashtra was part of the extended
region of rajputana which includes
which
goes all the way from rajasthan
up to sabrastra so it was the
rajput it was part of the rajput
heartland
and so on so this is a
bit about the history of saurashtra
so sabarashtra is part of gujarat but
the people of sabrasha speak a specific
kind of gujarati the pronunciation the
dialect is kind of different from
mainstream gujarati
uh it's called katyawadi gujarati kind
of you know
so that is so russia these are the
that's the people of the rashford now
there have been migrations out of
sabarashtra from time to time
into other parts of india
in tamil nadu there is
uh
in tamil nadu there are some people
called the swarastha people who speak a
language called the saurashtra language
so these are the the descendants
of people from saurashtra who migrated
to southern india about it looks like
about a thousand years ago
maybe because of the uh
arabic and turkic invasions that
happened somnath was destroyed etc so
many of these people migrated all the
way to southern india
and they still speak a language that is
derived from the ancient
prakriti language
that was once spoken about a thousand
years ago in saurashtra
right
and then there are the roman catholic
chatrias
of of uh
of goa etc they are called the chardo
people who are also descendants
of
people
who migrated there from saurashtra so
there is a little bit about the history
and the people of saurashtra it's a
fascinating region very interesting
history
and it is
once again a region that you we don't
really get to learn about in our history
textbooks
so yeah read about it it's very
interesting
okay why did turkish
invaders mongols etc always want to
invade india is it because of its
fabulous wealth or in the name of
religion
answer my question please okay first of
all the mongols
refused to invade india the great shri
changes khan was at the doorstep of
india
exactly eight hundred years ago today
in the year 1221
he defeated his enemy jalal deen of
kharasma
destroyed his army annihilated his army
and he saw jalaladin cross the indus
river
frantically
to escape with his life
and across the river
you had india the world's wealthiest
country and sri changes khan turned back
he was the doorstep of the richest
country in india in the world
and he he was the greatest conqueror in
human history in known history
so india was his for the taking and yet
he turned back so the mongols refused to
invade india a few a few decades later
there were some half-hearted half-hazard
attempts to nibble at the northern
borders of india but by the mongols but
there was never a serious invasion okay
when it comes to the to the turks yes
they did want to invade india they were
greedy little bastards
they wanted to invade india for the
wealth
and people like babur for example
uh
he
so babar was born in uh
in uzbekistan in the city of andhija and
he
had a couple of brothers i believe who
uh
who succeeded their father to the throne
so babar was left with nothing so he
took a bunch of followers and he crossed
over into afghanistan and india and he
managed to win
a small territory in northern india and
that's how the so-called mughal empire
was born right
so they the turks did it for the sake of
plunder for the sake of wealth because
they were greedy
and of course they did try and impose
their foreign religion in india and
we know that history very well so the
mongols
refused to invade india
the turks invaded india it was mostly
for wealth for plunder for for territory
right so that's what happened
okay
why does the world hate hindus and
polytheists
you see it's not hatred
it's that the world doesn't respect
hindus and polytheists
and the reason is very clear
what have we achieved in the past 1000
years
we are regarded hindus and polytheists
are regarded as the losers
because they have achieved nothing of
any significance in the past 1000 years
by the standards
that the west has set the standards of
greatness in the western world
are conquest and plunder
the more you conquer the more you
plunder
and the more you spread your foreign
culture and religion on foreign
territories and foreign peoples the
greater you are and the more you are
worthy of respect
that's why
barbarians like alexander
and genocidal
conquerors like julius caesar
are revered in the west
and today we all
basically follow western standards and
that's why
people like them
are revered and they are respected later
on the european conquerors
the conquistadors of southern america
the various colonizers of africa the
british who conquered india etc they are
glorified they exalted because they
succeeded in the conquests
and the hindus and the polytheists lost
and when you lose
you lose not just your territory and
your freedom you lose respect
you lose all your wealth and when you
become poor you lose
respect it is because of this that
hindus and polytheists
are not
hated
but they they they are not respected
and when hindus try to rise again
and when polytheists try to rise again
and bring their country back to its
former glory that's when the hatred
comes in because how dare you try to do
that stay down
stay in your lane
don't go off reservation and that sort
of thing so that is the actual sentiment
it is like they are contemptuous of the
polytheists and the hindus they don't
respect them and they want hindus and
polytheists so stay down stay poor stay
small don't think big don't be ambitious
don't have big dreams stay down
so that is the uh
overall general attitude
arunade haldar says is it
it is said that mother teresa came to
india in order to serve
people
but oftentimes historians
also claimed that she had another motive
like spreading christianity converting
people to our own religion etc please
throw some light on this
topic
okay
see uh this this individual teresa
she did not come to india to serve serve
anybody she came to india to serve her
religion and it is not i who is saying
this let me share my screen and
give you a book reference
i would urge you
to read
this book called
the missionary position
the author is christopher hitchens
in this book christopher hitchens who
happened to be british he no longer he's
no longer alive unfortunately he has
exposed this individual teresa
thoroughly he has exposed her thoroughly
everything about her she did not care
about anybody she did not care about
uplifting the poor she kept the people
of kolkata in poverty she had
immense funding from various places
she had access to hundreds of millions
of i'm not sure if it's hundreds of
millions of dollars but millions of
dollars
in funds
but she never uplifted these people from
poverty she kept them poor she kept them
in misery
and the only objective was to convert
convert convert
and this is
something that these missionaries have
done time and time again
not just in india in china as well they
would keep people poor they would
devastate the country
through wars and all that and then they
would offer people salvation in the form
of conversion so we will help you if you
convert let me show you something else
this is uh from 19th century china
during the opium wars
so china was devastated by the opium
wars okay there were many unequal
treaties that were imposed on china etc
and these
christian missionaries
would offer the poor chinese who were
starving
they would offer them salvation in the
form of conversion to christianity in
return they would give them rice
so the chinese would call these chinese
converse to christianity rice christians
this is what the chinese called chinese
converse to christianity they called
them rice christians so this is the same
tactic the christian missionaries like
teresa
have used in india that keep people in
crushing poverty and then they offer a
way out we will offer you a way out
we'll offer you food food and other
privileges if you convert
so this is the story of teresa and the
story of every christian
conversion mission anywhere in the world
kushi asks can or could could ancient
indians time travel
the answer in one word is no
deviating asks has any of the mughals
done anything good for india the answer
in one word is no
uh ishik asks
prithviraj raso claimed
was taken to gazna as ghazni is a
prisoner he was blinded the poet chand
bardai traveled to ghazni and tricked
muhammad of gore into watching an
archery performance by the blind
pithiraj during this performance
presurad shot the arrow in the direction
of muhammad's voice and killed him
after that prison chant bardai killed
each other is this true does it have any
historical evidence
the answer in one word is no
this is not true
hans deep says my family says that
sanskrit was just a language of
brahmanas it wasn't spoken in the whole
of india how can we change the mindset
of people and unleash the truth so
obviously this claim is false sanskrit
was the language of ancient india
whether it was vedic sanskrit whether it
was pre-vedic sanskrit
whether it was post vedic sanskrit or
whether it was
classical sanskrit from panini's time it
was the language of india it is only
later that the upper branch languages
came in the various prakrits like pali
et cetera
now people believe all kinds of
nonsense such as what you just said
because of our education system our
education system is full of distortions
the motto of india's education system is
and they have been brainwashing and
indoctrinating
generations of indians into believing
all these lies
now
what can we do to change the mindset of
people we cannot change the mindset of
people who have decided to believe
something it's impossible to change it
after a certain age people will refuse
to accept or entertain any new
information they said no what i believe
is what i believe everything else is
false
so that is the story with most people
what we can do
is we can
teach
the newer generations the truth
for that we have to change our history
textbooks we have to
detoxify our history textbooks so that
is something the government needs to do
i hope something is being done i've
heard there's this new education policy
which is taking some baby steps in some
certain directions there is some uh
some
hope in this in the form of new uh forms
of syllabus that have come out so i hope
something is being done about this what
needs to be done is this needs to happen
on a mass scale
india's history needs to be detoxified
it needs to be expunged of all these
lies
and then the newer generations will grow
up knowing the actual truth about our
history that's the best we can do we
cannot change the minds of people who
have been
believing these lies for decades it's
impossible to do that what we need to do
is we need to make sure the newer
generations the today's children today's
two-year-olds three-year-old
five-year-olds they grow up learning the
truth that's what needs to happen and
that is the job of the government of
india that's what we pay taxes for so i
hope that will be done
says considering the subcontinent shares
the same ethos but we are divided as a
people
what can be the catalyst to unite us
under one banner putting aside our
religious caste etc based differences
what kind of governance is suited
for our people
so that's what uh that's a very good
question of course so
india's strength we say is our diversity
we have one overarching culture and
civilization but within that we have so
many
different manifestations diverse
manifestations of that culture which
which sometimes seem to be very
different from each other so we have
this enormous amount of cultural
diversity we say it's our strength it is
also our greatest weakness because it
prevents us from unifying
when you have a mono culture like
christianity like islam like the han
culture like the chinese communist
party's culture etc then you can
easily unify
a nation but with our diversity
it is very hard to unify
us as a nation because all of us we
speak different dialects different
languages we worship the same gods in
different forms and today we have the
education system that is fragmenting us
further
so that is
india's great challenge it is the one
challenge india has been facing for the
past 1000 years and the solution is
leadership
the one thing india has lacked in the
past 1000 years
is a leader who is strong enough to
unify the nation
today india is unified under one
geographical landmass we have one
foreign constitution we have one set of
british laws
we have one parliament etc but we are so
disunited
our main hobby is to hate each other and
criticize each other and
snipe at each other that's all we do
we are so disunited we don't have
a leader strong enough
to get rid of the foreign constitution
to get rid of the fake syllabus in the
fake history
and to get rid of all these
international forces that are that seek
to fragment india and unify the nation
by force
with the strength of his or her will
that's what india lacks
so when india gets a leader like that
india will rise again until that time
nothing's going to happen now what kind
of governance is suited for for our
people well i think i just gave you the
answer
look back at the past few thousand years
of india's history
there have been times when india has
been disunited lots of small kingdoms
been unified under the great emperor
so look back at the times when india has
been unified india india has been a
great power
the mauryan empire
the empire of sri rama
the the bharat empire right
the kushan empire
the gupta empire
and so on
what are the unifying what are the
common characteristics you had of a
all-powerful centralized government
structure under one unifying leader
and of course you had localized
democratic forces
so that's the kind of thing india needs
india needs a strong
powerful central leadership
india has too much
what do you call it
what do they call it
federalism federalism is the word that's
used india's strength is its federal
structure
it is india's greatest weakness
there is too much democracy in india
like the chinese say
this fake democracy
which actually disempowers the people
and disempowers the country so india
needs a powerful strong central
leadership structure and india needs to
have local
democracy you can elect your local
town or council
leadership or your district leadership
but the central government has to be all
powerful only then can a sub continuous
con subcontinent size civilization be
strong and united so that's the kind of
governance structure india needs that's
the kind of governance structure we do
not have as of today and that my friends
is the answer
okay let me take a look at the live chat
do you have any questions that i can
answer quickly
no no no i i do not want to become the
pm now
no thank you very much
okay any questions any questions any
questions
something i can answer quickly
okay what's happening in kabul
what's happening in afghanistan yeah the
taliban are taking over i think they
have already entered kabul
the president the ex-president now mr
ashraf ghani has left afghanistan he's
on a plane as we speak
i'm not sure if he has landed somewhere
but he's out of afghanistan so
so yeah afghanistan is again once more
plunged into a dark age
a taliban age
so pakistan has one for
now the americans have
quit afghanistan
they have decided to they have decided
to leave afghanistan
to pakistan they handed it over to
pakistan
so like abhijit aramitra was saying
yesterday we need to sit back for some
time lick our wounds
and abide our time
yes what else do we have
yes good question by uh by spoder what
about the maratha empire was it not
strong enough it was strong enough to
reconquer much of the country
and at the end it was questions of
succession
and it was the infighting
that led to its
demise and that's why the british were
able to defeat the marathas over a
period of time
defeat in detail
it is always succession
that messes things up
if they had the right succession it if
it was
succession of the most powerful
uh
candidate for supremacy then the maratha
empire would have done well you see this
with with every empire whenever an
empire falls it's because the succession
has gone wrong and somebody weak comes
to power and that person is not able to
keep all you all the infighting down and
that's why all these
all these problems crop up and that's
how outside forces are able to defeat
you so the maratha empire did do a great
job of
reconquering much of india and in the
end it fell prey to its own weakness
which was infighting
and weakness of leadership
that is always the bane of any empire
any country
let me take one more question
something
what do we have
okay how did egypt lose its culture over
time and become islamic i think it began
with the uh conquest of egypt by the
romans by julius caesar
mark anthony etc that's how they lost
their original culture that's how became
they became
romanized hellenized to some extent
and uh eventually after the
after the
emergence of islam in in arabia
and the
outward expansion of all these various
caliphate forces it was a matter of time
before it fell
so in short that's how it became
islamized and there was a new caliphate
eventually which turned up which emerged
for some time
in egypt itself
before the ottoman empire took over the
reigns of the caliphate so that's in
very brief about
egypt
did the six rule over the afghanistan
region briefly here some parts of
afghanistan under maharaja ranjit singh
the six did defeat the afghans
and push them back out of kashmir out of
india and they did
rule some parts of what is now called
pashtunistan which is on either side of
the durant of the
current durand line which is the de
facto pakistan afghanistan border
so yes they did
rule over
parts of india which were inhabited by
pashtuns they did rule over part of the
pashtun
heartland the homeland so yes they did
rule over parts of afghanistan
in short that's the answer
one
final question
what should i do to become a real hindu
learn sanskrit
learn sanskrit that's it
okay my friends thank you so much it was
a great session wonderful questions i
really appreciate it
this brings us to the end of today
today's session thank you so much for
all your questions thank you for your
viewership i will see you
very soon in the next episode
until then take care have a good day
have a good night
see you soon